So, in another video, in this video, we will discuss about the TCP and UDP of briefly.
So, there is a different speed between TCP and UDP.
So, we all know that TCP will be added in the TCP and UDP will be added in the transport
player.
It is a protocol.
So, we need the difference between both of this protocol, what is the future of the protocols.
So, why we are using TCP in many places and why we are using UDP in video streaming applications.
So, let us start with our discussion.
So, if you see, let us see the TCP first.
So, we will say the TCP is a connection oriented protocol, okay.
In the first point, it is a connection oriented protocol.
So, it means like the sender, u and the server will be connected each other till the completion
of the process, okay.
So, if you are communicating with the server till the communication, you both are connected.
Your connection will be maintained, okay.
So, we are saying it is a connection oriented protocol.
So, apart from that, the TCP is used in the applications, like if you are sending some high
message to one of your friend in WhatsApp, the packet will not be missed, right.
So, if you are sending a big paragraph, the packet will not be missed and we will give
a few runs to the packet, it will be reached to your destination, your target server, right.
So, it is like a safe query, so whatever you are sending a sequence, it will be received
to the destination proper limit of any missing of packets, without any missing of this
character, okay.
There is not only a character, but if you are sending some user names and password, so
this both will be shared to the server, right.
So, if anyone of the impostor, anyone of the character will be missed, then the website
send an error, like there is a mistake in username and password, so we are using TCP there,
okay.
So, the TCP will give a sequence to your packet, it will be received to the receiver,
all the packets will be received to the receiver, okay, in TCP.
But if you see in UDP, it is a very fast service, very fast protocol, okay.
The TCP is slow, it is very slow compared to UDP, so UDP we are using in video streaming
applications like IMO video calls and YouTube streaming and some video applications like
Zoom are anything, okay.
So, in here, if your internet connection has an issue, or if your network speed was reduced,
some packets will be missed, right.
So this needs to in UDP, so there are two things audio and videos will be shared accordingly,
right.
So, you may face some issues there, so sometime in IMO, your audio will be given to you
after some minutes of the video or the video will be present to you after some minutes
of audio, right.
So there are some issues in UDP, okay, there is, we can't give a sequence every packet
will be received to the receiver, so UDP has a drawback for that, okay.
So, UDP is very fast, so we are using the UDP in most of the video streaming applications
and video streaming application, the videos and audio needs to be transferred to the receiver
continuously with the audio and video.
So it need the protocol needs to be very faster, so we are not using TCP here, okay.
So now let's discuss how TCP sharing the packets without any of the interference, okay.
Basically, TCP have a pre-way handshake, okay, so CINAC and that it's like high there, so
this receiver will send a high, okay, high, I am here, okay.
And I will send some packets to you, so this like high, high I am live, I am going to send
some packets to you, that is an acknowledgement, okay.
CIN is a high, CINAC is a, I am here, high I am here and ACT is a, I am going to send
some packets to you, okay.
But if you see in UDP, so it's a reduced response, right, so whatever you are sending,
it will be transferred directly to the receiver, it will not, there is no handshake, there
is no, nothing CINAC packets will be shared before that, okay.
So that's why there handshake in between TCP and UDP, so that's why the TCP was a bit
slower comparing to the UDP and if you see in UDP, sorry, if you see in TCP, there is
one of the features, has a TCP, like error control, okay, there is an error control and
there is a segment number, numbering system, okay, every data, every data, we discussed
about all the segments, right, in transport layer, every data will be segmented, right.
So IP destination IP will be added, for Mac and destination Mac will be added, we'll discuss
that in previous video, so every data has a segment number, sequence, sorry, sequence number,
SCC, sequence equal to 1, sequence equal to 2, sequence equal to 3, and sequence, sequence
equal to 1000, okay, so some time, if the sequence number 3 was missed, so in, this is
a sender, so let's come up with a receiver, in the receiver side, receiver received sequence
number 1 packet, received sequence number 2 packet, and receiver received sequence
number 4th packet instead of third packet, okay, third packet will be missed, okay.
So now what TCP will do, it will arrange all the packets, okay, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6,000, okay,
so then it will check what are the packets are missed, so it will identify, there's a packet,
packet number 3 was missed, okay, so now what TCP will do, TCP will ask the sender to
raise, recent this third packet, okay, recent this third packet, because there's a data loss,
okay, the third packet will be lost, so the TCP will ask the sender to give a third packet
one more time, okay, now sender will transform the third packet to the receiver, so that
we are saying TCP has a better mechanism comparing to UDP, so whatever we are sending from
TCP, everything will be arrived to your receiver properly, okay, without any interference,
okay, so now discuss about the UDP, okay, UDP will be much faster than TCP, there's no
handshakes and no error control mechanism, no error control, okay, no error control, okay,
so we will say this is error control, okay, so there's an error, there's a packet will
be missed, so we are saying that error control mechanism was implemented in TCP and there,
in UDP there is no error control mechanism, so it's the packet was missed, so the packet
will not be, the UDP will not ask that packet send one more time to the sender, okay, so UDP
will not ask the packet to send one more time, okay, if the packet was missed it will be, the
UDP will not worry, it will just transfer whatever's saying, okay, it will just transfer
other data, whatever's saying, it will not care about the packet, so we will not give
any assurance to your packet if you are sending to UDP, so that's where in video streaming
applications, some of the packets will be missed and you can't able to hear the voice or
you can't able to see the video in between if there is a communication issue, okay, so
next one also the TCP has a flow control mechanism, so there's a flow control mechanism will
be implemented in TCP, so it will send the data, it will see what's the limit of the limits
to transfer the data, okay, it will limit that data to transfer it to the receiver, okay,
because to ensure the reliable delivery, all the data will be received to the receiver,
no data will be lost, okay, there's a flow control mechanisms are there, okay, flow control
is mechanism is basically a data transferring mechanism, so if you're sending all the data
in a fast manner, in a very fast manner, then many data will be missed, okay, so TCP will
set a flow control mechanism for that and it will send the data on by one, okay, so it
will check the capability, how much data we can send and it will send the sent data, okay,
so that's all about this video, it's a difference between the TCP and the UDP, okay, hope
you enjoyed the video, so no worry some parts will be theory here because you need to understand
what's networking and what's the concept of the networking we already said in the previous
sessions, yep, thanks for watching the video, we will see you in the next video, bye-bye.